All right. בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So we start the fourth פרק,
perek, דף ס"ח ס"ח, Daf Samech-Chet Samech-Chet, as we just said, you
know, the last פרק perek אלו טרפות Eilu Treifos was a major
accomplishment. I don't know, what was it, thirty דף? daf? Something like
that. It was a very nice huge size and also so many
critical topics in terms of טרפות, treifos, which was very challenging in
terms of whole biology and anatomy or whatever, and then כשרות kashrus
non-כשרות kashrus species, obviously very, very relevant for practical כשרות. kashrus. This
fourth פרק perek is much more theoretical discussions and interesting conceptual discussions
before we get back to more, more practical issues. And we start
with field שוחט-ing shochet an animal and wanting to eat its meat,
but having to worry about what happens about the potential of the
עובר ubbar that is found in the mother's womb when the mother
is שוחט-ed, shochet which as you know, it's called the בן פקועה,
ben pakua, and that the שחיטה shechita of the mother works for
the עובר ubbar because until the עובר ubbar is born, it is
considered to be a part of the mother, although not exactly the
same as other limbs, as the first משנה Mishna will make clear.
And at what stage is the עובר ubbar actually considered born? So
those are the types of questions that we're dealing with. So let's
take a look here from the beginning of the משנה, Mishna, ס"ח
עמוד א'. Samech-Chet amud aleph. בהמה המקשה לילד, Behema hamaksha leiled, an
animal that is having a difficulty in childbirth. So basically it means
that it's in the process of childbirth. The fact that it's having
difficulty is not so relevant other than that it basically means that
it's not happening like instantaneously.
הוציא העובר ידו והחזירה, hotzi ha-ubbar yado vehechzira, and the עובר ubbar
stuck out a limb, literally its arm, and then brought it back
in. It's sort of like what was it, פרץ Paretz and זרח?
Zerach? Anyway, right, and then you שוחט shochet it.
מותר באכילה, mutar baachila, then it is permissible, and then you שוחט
shochet it, it's permissible to be eaten.
הוציא את ראשו,
hotzi
et rosho, no, no, you שוחט shochet the mother, you שוחט shochet
the mother. Now you can eat it. Now the question the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask is, what is the 'it'? Obviously the
'it' means you can eat the עובר. ubbar. Why would the hand
make a difference for that? Or maybe not, but does the 'it'
also perhaps mean you can even eat the limb? Or the fact
that the limb went out, that means that the limb remains forbidden?
We'll talk about that in a minute. But there's no sense of
that, no, no, you didn't start the שחיטה. shechita. There's no sense
of that in the משנה. Mishna. Ah, so the simple, okay. So
הוציא
את ראשו, hotzi et rosho, אף על פי שהחזירו, af al pi
shehecheziro, if it poked its head out of the womb and then
pulled it back in, and then you שוחט-ed shochet the mother,
הרי זה כילוד, harei zeh k'yalud, the עובר ubbar is like it's
already born, and the שחיטה shechita for the mother does not help
for the עובר. ubbar. Well, let's assume רובו rubbo of its head.
Okay. חת chat is all, but it was actually רובו. rubbo. Okay.
So it, well, or breathed or whether it breathes or not. The
idea when the head comes out, you know, it's considered as if
it is born. So the simple sense of this משנה Mishna is
basically telling you, the שחיטה shechita of the mother works for the
infant, as long as the עובר ubbar is not yet born. At
what stage is the עובר ubbar considered born? When the head comes
out, and even if it pulled it back in and now it's
fully in the mother's womb, it still was considered born. Okay. And
it's really not addressing the question of was there a problem with
the one limb, the arm? Is the arm permissible, not permissible? The
focus here is when is the עובר ubbar considered born. But we
will see about the discussion about the arm in the גמרא. Gemara.
If it takes out everything but its head, it's not considered born?
No, that would be considered born, that would be a different status
of רובו. rubbo. But that's not discussed in the משנה. Mishna. Okay,
now, actually, those raise an interest, well, yeah, I assume by all
mammals it's the same and that crowning and the head coming is
the natural form of birth. So if you say ראשו, rosho, you
know, then that is כילוד, k'yalud, you don't have to say anything
else except for, you know, an unnatural situation where it's coming out,
you know, as a breech baby or something like that.
Or a C-section and you, like, you know, take it out with
the head last?
That's true, that raises questions about right, at what stage is a
C-section infant considered born because that's a separate question. Yes. Good.
Well, there are five species of mammals that lay eggs, but they
aren't כשר, kosher, so, right.
Okay. There you go. All right. חותך מעובר שבמעיה, chotech me-ubbar shebim'eha,
now,
someone cut up the עובר ubbar in the mother's womb, and the
parts of the עובר ubbar are still sitting in the womb when
the mother is שוחט-ed. shochet Okay, so does the שחיטה shechita of
the mother work for a dismembered עובר ubbar in the mother's womb?
And the answer is yes. Why? They're still in the animal and
the שחיטה shechita of the mother still works for them. Okay, but
look at the next line. מן הטחול ומן הכליות, min hat'chol umin
haklayos, if however, a person stuck his hand into the insides of
an animal while it was alive and cut the spleen or the
kidneys. Now, it specifically mentions spleen or kidneys because for those who
remember from last פרק, perek, if an animal has a detached spleen
or kidney, it is not a טרפה. treifa. So you cut the
spleen or kidneys
and you did not make it a טרפה. treifa. And now the
spleen and kidneys are just sitting inside the, what's it called, cavity.
of the animal, okay? And you שחט shecht the animal. Does the
שחיטה shechitah work on the disconnected spleen and kidney? So it says
אסור באכילה. Asur Be'achilah. No, those you cannot eat. So you've got
a dismembered fetus inside the mother and you שחט shecht the mother,
it works for the fetus. You have a dismembered spleen or whatever,
detached spleen or kidneys and you שחט shecht the animal, it does
not work to kosher the spleen and kidneys. Fetus? No, no, no.
No fetus in the second case of the actual mother. Okay, what
it is saying is to what degree, it's a great illustration of,
we often say, you know, עובר ירך אמו, Ubar yerech imo, fetus
like a limb of the mother. But is it really? Okay, because
if you think about it, a fetus even when it's in the
mother's womb has its own sort of independent life that is growing
there that is being supported by the mother. So that's why you
can have a debate, is it like a limb of the mother?
To some degree yes, to some degree now. So what it's saying
here is, is that something like an actual organ, a spleen or
a kidney, when you cut them when the mother is still alive,
what they actually become, here's the key point, is אבר מן החי.
Ever min hachai. When you cut an organ when the animal was
still alive from the animal and so the animal hasn't had שחיטה,
shechitah, it's an intrinsic organ of the animal, part of the animal,
and cutting it makes that thing an אבר מן החי, Ever min
hachai, a detached limb from a live thing. And therefore שחט shechting
the mother afterwards won't help, it already became an אבר מן החי.
Ever min hachai. Whereas when you cut the fetus, although we say
the fetus is, can be like ירך אמו, yerech imo, it's not
a natural part of the mother, it's not an intrinsic part of
the mother, right? It's going to get born, it has its own
life even when it's there. So cutting it from the mother does
not make it an אבר מן החי. Ever min hachai. And since
when you cut it up in the mother's womb you didn't make
it an אבר מן החי, Ever min hachai, and when you שחט
shecht the mother still inside the mother, it's still considered to be
enough within the mother that the שחיטה shechitah of the mother works
for it. Okay, so what it actually is, it's a nice illustration
of, you know, that when we say a fetus is the limb
of the mother, we don't mean it a hundred percent. You know,
it does have its own independence, it's not fully a limb and
therefore cutting it from the mother does not make it אבר מן
החי, Ever min hachai, you know, because from the very beginning it
was not fully a part of the mother to begin with. Okay,
so that's that part of the משנה. Mishnah. זה הכלל, Zeh Haklal,
this is the principle.
This has to do with the עובר, Ubar, right? I mean מן
הטחול והכליות min ha'tchol ve'haklayot then regardless of whether there's an עובר
Ubar or...
It's comparing spleen and kidney to fetus. It's not spleen and kidney
of fetus, it's comparing one thing that is within an animal to
another thing within an animal. The spleen and kidney is an intrinsic
part of the animal. The fetus, while it might be as if
it's part of the animal, is not really part of the animal.
And therefore it has this state, cutting it when the animal's alive
does not make it אבר מן החי. Ever min hachai.
Right, the spleen and the kidneys are of the animal itself. In
this case, it would have been any other...
Yes, but putting it here contrasts it to the fetus.
Spleen and kidney of the mother.
Yes. The second case might not even be a mother, you know?
As it says, it's not clear.
Right, right, right. זה
הכלל, Zeh Haklal, this is the principle. דבר שגופה אסור, Davar shegufah
asur,
something that is really part of the animal, when you cut it
and the animal's alive, is forbidden, that becomes an אבר מן החי.
Ever min hachai. ושאינו גופה, Veshe'eino gufah,
something that is not literally part of the mother, like the fetus,
מותר, mutar, if you cut it when the mother is alive, it
will become permissible, the שחיטה shechitah of the mother will work for
it. So the end of the משנה Mishnah is a nice... this
whole משנה Mishnah is about the שחיטה shechitah of the mother working
for the fetus. And the beginning is when is the fetus considered
born, and the end is, you know, to what degree is the
fetus considered literally a part of the mother. The שחיטה shechitah of
the mother can work for the fetus, but we're not saying the
fetus is literally a part of the mother, and that's illustrated by
the last contrast between the fetus and a spleen and a kidney.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara
starts with the first part about that. So, אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, so says the
גמרא, Gemara, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav,
so says Rav Yehuda in the name of Rav, ואבר עצמו אסור.
Ve'ever atzmo asur. Now Rav here introduces, or Rav Yehuda in Rav's
name introduces, a new idea which was not mentioned in the משנה
Mishnah at all. He says when the limb goes out, the משנה
Mishnah says the limb goes out and comes back, the emphasis of
the משנה Mishnah here is the fetus is not born yet, the
שחיטה shechitah of the mother works for the fetus. Says Rav Yehuda
in Rav's name, but the limb going out, the act that a
limb went out while the fetus was in there makes that limb
forbidden. And that limb remains forbidden even after it gets pulled back
into the mother's womb. Now that's bizarre, because I would have said
while the limb is out, if you ask me what happens now
if I'm going to שחט shecht the mother with the fetus with
one limb out, I would say fine, the שחיטה shechitah will work
with the part that's in the womb and it doesn't work on
the part not in the womb. Okay, so the שחיטה shechitah can't
yet work, can't work in this state on this limb outside. But
why does the limb become forbidden, get a status of being forbidden,
and why even when it's pulled back does it remain forbidden? So
that's not in the משנה Mishnah at all.
But then at most you would say the fetus would be permitted,
right? And right, at most you would say maybe I just have
to שחט shecht the fetus in order to make, right? And he's
saying you can't do that. He's saying this limb becomes forbidden. Not
only does the שחיטה shechitah of the mother no longer work for
it, it will always be forbidden even if you were to שחט
shecht the fetus. Yes.
Well, that even if you were to שחט shecht the fetus, the
fetus would have to be alive...
Right, meaning even if you were to שחט shecht *shecht* the mother,
take the fetus out of the mother's womb, or even if the
fetus were now to be born, and then you were to שחט
shecht *shecht* the fetus, this limb remains forbidden. Right. Now, if the
fetus let me qualify that. He hasn't said it yet, and I'll
clarify that, but let me qualify that. If it sticks out the
limb and then continues to be born, then obviously you שחט shecht
*shecht* the fetus, that's just the birth of an animal and you
שחט shecht *shecht* the fetus. But if it sticks out the limb
and does not continue to be born, and in the end comes
from the womb of the mother after שחיטה shechitah *shechita*, then that
limb, because it went out and was not part of the birth
of the animal, remains a forbidden limb. This is a new idea.
Where do we even get this from? So let's take a look.
The opposite of זה הכלל *zeh haklal*, because according to זה הכלל
*zeh haklal*, if it's אינה גופה *eina gufa*, it's מותר *mutar*.
That was without the sticking out of the limb, that was the
issue about when you cut something up within the mother.
But you're making a general כלל *klal* here.
Yeah, I know, but you could also say that זה הכלל *zeh
haklal* goes against when it sticks the head out, it's not מותר
*mutar*. So זה הכלל *zeh haklal* is within the context of at
what stage cutting up makes a difference. Here's a different issue of
sticking out the limb. So let's take a look. So ואבר שיצא
אסור assur *ve'eivar sheyatza asur*. מאי טעמא taima *mai ta'ama*? What's the
reason? דאמר קרא *d'amar kra*, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says, ובשר בשדה
basadeh, טרפה treifa לא lo תאכלו *u'vasar basadeh tereifah lo tocheilu*, and
meat in a field that is torn you shall not eat. So
we normally ignore the word בשדה besadeh, *basadeh*, in the field, for
הלכה halacha *halacha* purposes because we emphasize the word טרפה treifa. *tereifah*.
But here we're going to emphasize the word בשדה *basadeh*, and we're
going to say the following: כיון שיצא בשר חוץ למחיצתו chutz lemchitzato
*keivan sheyatza basar chutz limechitzato*,
once the meat went into the field it doesn't say, but here's
the point outside of its boundaries, like field is outdoors, out there,
outside of its home, outside of its boundaries, then נאסר *ne'esar*, it
becomes forbidden. Now, what does this mean? Well, we're going to see
in a little bit later in today's דף *daf* that this starts
with an idea that's applied to when sacrificial meat is taken outside
of the space where it's allowed to be eaten. So for example,
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim *kodshei kodashim*, like a חטאת chatat. *chatat*, which
should only be eaten in the temple precincts, right? Only in the
actual not even in הר הבית *har habayis*, it has to be
actually in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *beis hamikdash* itself. קדשים קלים
kodashim kalim *kodashim kalim*, like a שלמים shelamim *shlamim*, can be eaten
in all of ירושלים Yerushalayim. *yerushalayim*. What happens if I take the
meat outside? I take the meat of the שלמים *shlamim* outside of
ירושלים Yerushalayim *yerushalayim*. I take the meat of a חטאת chatat, *chatat*
out of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *beis hamikdash*. Can I say
'Whoops!' and put it back in and then eat it? Or does
the fact that it left the zone, the right zone, automatically make
it forbidden? Right? So that's what we say. We say, yeah, as
soon as it leaves its right zone, it becomes forbidden. Now, you
can understand intuitively that concept. That has קדושה *kedusha*, that has sanctity.
The sanctity defines the acceptable space. Somehow that sanctity is somehow compromised,
impinged upon when it's in a wrong space, so that leads to
an invalidity. But that we learn that idea from this פסוק pasuk.
*pasuk*, believe it or not, of meat in the field, meat that
goes out of its zone, out of its home, being out in
the field becomes like a טרפה treifa. *tereifah*, becomes forbidden. But again,
it would be one thing to apply that to a case where
we have an intuitive sense that that should make sense, like sacrifices
that go out of their right space. But here what רב יהודה
אמר רב Rav Yehuda amar Rav. *rav yehuda amar rav* is doing
is he's applying that to even this fetus that is in its
space, its space is the mother's womb, and the limb goes out
of that space. Now if it's again, as I said before, in
the process of being born, that's not having violated its space, it's
doing a transition and it's being born. But if it stuck out
the arm and then you שחט shecht *shecht* it, so from the
perspective of where it ended up, where is the space of that
fetus? If the only sort of acceptable space for it, given that
you שחט shecht *shecht* the mother, is within the mother's womb? Because
that's what allowed the שחיטה shechitah *shechita* of the mother to work
for it. So in that context, this thing was offsides
in terms of where we're going to need it to be looking
in the end, because it's not going to be born in the
end. Looking in the end when we're going to שחט shecht *shecht*
the mother, we're going to need this to be in the womb.
So here we say, so since it was sort of out of
bounds right? What happens if you step out of bounds? You can't
come back for that play, right? So if it steps out of
bounds, right, it can't come back, even if it pulls itself back,
right, if you שחט shechted *shecht* the mother, that remains out of
bounds as it were. And therefore that limb remains forbidden even if
it gets pulled back. That is what he is saying. It's not
in the משנה Mishnah. *mishna*, it's a big חידוש chiddush *chiddush*, conceptually
it's also a little strange idea, but that is what he is
saying.
So it stuck its arm out, it put it back in, you
שחט shechted *shecht* the mother, you can never have that though
you can never have that limb.
So when you say limb, like
arm
or is it like
a hoof, the whole leg? Anything, whatever part stuck out.
No, no, but if the hoof is attached to the leg, does
that mean the whole leg is forbidden or just the hoof?
No, just the hoof up to the part that is exposed to
the air, the part that is outside of the mother.
So the אבר *eivar* just means a part of it, not the
whole right, exactly.
Okay, so that is his idea.
Do you need to believe that if it does that, do you
need to tie something to it or something? Because you don't know
if it's the back leg or the front leg or the left
leg.
Right, right, again, it's really like a פרץ *Perez* and זרח *Zerach*
case.
So it's possible then for a mother to be in the process
of giving birth and for a fetus... to extend a limb and
then return it and then die, and meanwhile, the person who owns
the animal isn't there to see it.
Right, oh that's true too. But you can't worry about what you
can't see. I mean, if you have no reason to suspect that
happened, right, then you don't have to worry about it, right? And
so, you know, you could have other cases. Somebody reports it happens,
do you have to believe that person? If that person, you know,
maybe they're making something up, you know, dah dah dah. So right,
but there's a lot of things. And let's say I'm doing a
factory and I'm making food and something טריף falls into the vat
and I'm not there to see it, you know, what are you
supposed to do, you know? But you can't address cases you don't
know about. All right.
But yes, it's in the משנה.
Mishnah, It's not in the משנה, Mishnah it's the opposite. The opposite.
Ah, so the משנה Mishnah says, right. So the משנה Mishnah, says
it's permissible. So the גמרא Gemara is going to ask, what's permissible?
The fetus or the limb? Now there's two ways to argue on
this, and we're going to see both. One way to argue on
it is, is that the limb is, you know, never becomes forbidden
in the first place. There's not this concept at all about that
חוץ למחיצתו other than by קרבנות. korbanot. The other possibility is while
the limb is out, it's a problem because the שחיטה shechitah of
the mother doesn't apply to the limb, but as soon as you
pull the limb back in, it becomes permissible, right, which is really
the same thing. It's saying there's not a concept that having gone
offsides, you remain invalid. Just as long as the limb is out,
the שחיטה shechita doesn't apply to it. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says תנן, tnan, we
taught in our משנה, Mishnah, בהמה המקשה לילד והוציא עובר ידו והחזירה
מותר באכילה. beheimah hamakshah leleled vehotzia ubar yado vehachzirah mutar baachilah. So
it's the fetus stuck out the limb and pulled it back, it's
permissible to be eaten. So you see that if it pulls back
the limb, and then you שחט shecht it, you can eat the
limb. מאי לאו אבר? mai lav eivar? Does that not mean that
the limb now becomes permissible, can now be eaten since it was
pulled back? גמרא Gemara says לא אעובר. lo aubbar. No, not on
the, it's almost very similar sounding words. Not on the limb, but
on the fetus. It means that the sticking out the limb is
not like it's born, so the שחיטה shechita of the mother still
works for the fetus, but the limb, that will remain forbidden. And
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, אי אעובר, ei aubbar, if it's
only telling me that the fetus is permissible, מאי איריא דהחזירו? mai
irya dehachziro? Why does it have to say it pulled the limb
back? Right, the point is to tell me sticking out a limb
is not like it's born yet. So there's no point about saying
the limb, the pulled the limb back. The only reason to say
pulled the limb back was to tell me even the limb now
can be eaten because it was pulled back.
No, anything, it's more in the process of being born if the
limb is still out. So if you're trying to tell me even
if it pulled the limb out, it's not yet born, you could
tell me even though the limb is hanging out, it's not considered
born. Okay, it's less considered born when it pulls the limb back.
So אי אעובר מאי איריא דהחזירו, ei aubbar mai irya dehachziro, if
you're only telling me that the fetus is okay and it's not
born, why did you give the scenario that it pulled the limb
back? אפילו לא החזיר נמי, afilu lo hechzir nami,
even without pulling the limb back, it's not considered born since it's
only a limb. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know what, you're
right. הוא הדין אף על גב דלא החזיר. hu hadin af al
gav delo hechzir. Yes, if we were just telling me the חידוש
chiddush, that the fetus is not born, it would not have said
pulled back. It would have said it sticks out the limb and
you שחט shecht it now, it's not born. Okay, ואיידי דקבעי למיתני
סיפא, ve'aidi deka ba'ei lemisni seifa,
but because the end of the משנה, Mishnah. which is our real
point, what are we going to say at the end? הוציא ראשו
אף על פי שהחזירו הרי זה כילוד, hotzia rosho af al pi
shehachziro harei zeh keyalud,
when it sticks out its head, even if it pulls the head
back, it's like it's born. That's the real point of the משנה.
Mishnah, At what stage is the fetus considered born? Not when it
sticks out a limb, when it sticks out its head. And not
only that, once it sticks out its head, even if it pulls
the head back, it's already considered born. That's a חידוש, chiddush right?
So since we're going to say the end scenario to say that
it's born when it sticks out the head, and even if it
pulled the head back, there we're going to say even though it
pulled it back, ואיידי דקבעי למיתני סיפא הוציא ראשו אף על פי
שהחזירו הרי זה כילוד. ve'aidi deka ba'ei lemisni seifa hotzia rosho af
al pi shehachziro harei zeh keyalud. We're going to say at the
end that it's like it's born even if it pulled the head
back. תנא נמי רישא
החזיר. tana nami reisha hechzir. In the beginning, it also gave a
scenario of pulling the limb back. But the point of the משנה,
Mishnah and although this sounds a little bit like a stretch, really,
it's true. Our משנה Mishnah is ignoring the issue about the כשרות
kashrus of the limb. Now you could say because it's ignoring it,
it's implying that it's kosher, but regardless, the משנה's Mishnah? point is
to tell you when a limb is not like it's born, a
head is like it's born even if it pulled the head back.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says don't get hung up about the
pulling the limb back, that wasn't the point. All right, and yes,
we can still assert that the limb is forbidden. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, ומאי קמשמע לן סיפא מאי קמשמע לן? umai
kamashma lan seifa mai kamashma lan? And what's the point of the
end of the משנה? Mishnah, דכיון דיצא ראשו הוה ליה כילוד, dekivan
deyatzah rosho havei lei keyalud, that once the head is out, it's
considered to be born. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say
that can't be the whole point of the משנה, Mishnah that the
whole point of the משנה Mishnah is the end discussion about the
head. Why? Because תנינא, tanina, we already know that from other sources.
We know it from another משנה Mishnah, that it's considered born once
the head already comes out. And this is an assumption that something
we know from some other משנה, Mishnah, we wouldn't bother to teach
me in another context, which is a little bit funny. Okay, but
anyway, it says that can't be the whole point of the משנה,
mishna because we already know that idea that the head coming out
is considered born. How do we know that?
איזהו בכור לנחלה ואינו בכור לכהנים. eizehu bechor lenachalah ve'eino bechor lekohanim.
So now we're going to shift from animals to humans. The גמרא
Gemara in a minute will question the comparison, but the point is
like this. So by humans, right, being a בכור bechor has a
couple of significant implications. One significant implication is, is that like we're
actually
about to read in a week, that he gets the double portion,
right. The firstborn gets the double portion. The other implication about being
a firstborn is you have to do a פדיון. pidyon. You have
to, right? Because of a firstborn. What defines a בכור bechor for
those two are not the same. What defines a בכור bechor for
פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen is פטר רחם, peter rechem, the opening, the
breaching of the womb. What defines a firstborn for the double portion,
the פסוק pasuk says הוא ראשית אונו, Hu reishis ono, the first
of his strength. What does that mean? Well, first of all, one
difference
is, whether it's the father's firstborn or the mother's firstborn. Right, there
could be multiple firstborns for פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen and only one
firstborn for נחלה nachalah is the father's firstborn. But that's not the
point here. The point here is, what if it precede, what if
before the birth of the child there were miscarriages? So from the
perspective of the first of his strength, the גמרא Gemara learns out
that the child has to have been, that only a viable child
is considered to have been a firstborn for inheritance. So if there
were a couple of miscarriages and then a viable child was born,
he would get a double portion. If there was a viable child
who then died and then there was another child, that would be,
then that second type would not be the firstborn. It is the
first viable child. The first viable child, what?
Miscarriages or stillborns?
Either way, either way. Yeah, someone just like Lazer. But either way,
okay, it's the first viable child is the double portion. Whereas for
פדיון, pidyon, besides being about the mother as I, and this is
related to it, it is the first thing that has breached the
womb. Therefore, it is the first type of, once, even a miscarriage,
once it's considered to have been some formed fetus of like 40
days or whatever, even a miscarriage means that what comes afterwards is
no longer the first to have breached the womb. So you can
have something that is a firstborn for inheritance because he comes after
miscarriages, but not a firstborn for פדיון. pidyon. So let's just read
that inside. So it says like this.
איזהו בכור, Eizehu bechor, what?
מסכת בכורות. Masechet Bechoros. Firstborn
girl?
Firstborn girl is neither.
Neither פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen nor double portion. Right, both cases it
has to be a boy. What about a Caesarean? Right, Caesarean also.
But also, he would be a בכור לפי שניים, bechor l'pi shnayim,
right?
Interesting question.
I'd have to
check.
You'd have to check. Okay, so okay, so okay, so. איזהו בכור
לנחלה ואינו בכור לכהנים, Eizehu bechor l'nachalah v'eino bechor l'kohanim,
what is a בכור bechor for inheritance, the double portion, and not
a בכור bechor for כהנים, kohanim, meaning for the need of פדיון?
pidyon? הבא אחרי נפלים, Habah acharei nefalim, something that came, a child
that was born after miscarriages. Now נפלים nefalim can either mean miscarriages,
and as I explained that, so therefore, or stillborns and as I
explained, it's the first viable child but not the first to have
breached the womb. נפלים nefalim also in this context means, the גמרא
Gemara assumed that any child, any born in the eighth month, right,
before nine months were completed, it was not viable. So even if
it was born alive, it would have been considered effectively a miscarriage
waiting to be happened. Like you know you can have a live
birth, but if it was not a nine-month child, the גמרא Gemara
would have considered it a non-viable child. So therefore, if you have
a child born, now of course you know what the גמרא Gemara
would have done because by the time the second child is born,
unless they're twins, but by the time how's the twins they were
both non, so whatever, by the time the second child was born,
the first one would have already lived, you know, but the גמרא
Gemara even assumes that even if the eight-month baby lives for, you
know, for years, it's considered like you're just waiting for him to
die. Like the גמרא Gemara assumes that he really wasn't viable unless
he hit 20 years old. Then maybe he would already establish a
חזקה. hazakah. So on my, I was born in the eighth month.
So on my 20th birthday, I had a celebration for being a
בן קיימא. ben kayama. So I don't know but anyway, but what
if the baby dies after being alive for eight days? Yeah, what
does, how does that affect the next child who's born? Nothing, it
doesn't matter the eight days. The question is whether it was born
after it had been, you know, in the eighth month or in
the ninth month was really the question, whether it was considered viable
or not. Sometimes we have to wait till the end of 30
days. Sometimes we say that the first month is a doubtful whether
it's a בן קיימא ben kayama and after 30 days it's assumed
to be a בן קיימא ben kayama for certain doubts about whether
it had a full gestation or not. So anyway, let me just
finish the point. So therefore, a child born either after a real
stillborn miscarriage or after an eight-month-old baby, which is effectively considered the
same even if the child stays alive, so therefore the first one
was considered to be a non-viable birth, but that breached the womb.
The second one is the first viable birth. So therefore the second
one is a בכור bechor for the double portion because it's the
first viable birth, but not for פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen because it
did not breach the womb. Okay, so even if you're 20 years
old and you don't do a פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen afterwards? What?
If you're the first, nowadays we really don't go by the eight-month
thing, but that's a separate conversation, okay? Basically nowadays we say, oh
well you know there was a viable child even though it was
born within the eight months, it was really a nine-month-old baby born
early or something like that. So yeah, but I'm not getting into,
yeah, so I'm not getting into that discussion now. Okay. So איזהו
זה הבא אחר נפלים eizehu ze haba achar nefalim a child that
is born after again either stillborns or non-viable births, אף על פי
שיצא ראשו חי af al pi sheyatza rosho chai even though this
eight-month-old baby, you know, eight-month gestated baby comes out alive with its
head alive. So even though it's living when it's born, it's not
considered viable,
או o or a more standard case that we would assume, בן
תשעה שיצא ראשו מת ben tesha sheyatza rosho met even if it
was a full, fully gestated baby, but it came out dead, stillborn,
in either of those cases, right, the second child is not is
the first viable child but not the first who breaches the womb.
So in those
cases, so that's our example of being a firstborn for for inheritance
and not for כהנים. kohanim. Now, why is this relevant for us?
It's relevant for us because it speaks about coming the head coming
out. So it says like this, טעמא the reason the fully gestated
baby was not considered to have been viable was because דראשו מת
derosho met because when its head came out, it was already dead.
הא ראשו חי ha rosho chai if when its head came out
it was alive and then it died after, the implication of this
משנה mishna is that as soon as if it was a fully
gestated baby and when the head came out it was alive, that
would have been considered to have been the first viable birth. And
so there you can infer that it is considered to have been
born from the moment the head comes out.
Isn't this obvious first for all that from... Yes, right.
Okay, anyway, הבא אחריו בכור לנחלה נמי לא
הוי haba achrav bechor lenachala nami lo havi so if the head
came out and it was still and it was alive at the
moment the head came out, it would have been considered to be
the first viable birth and the second child would not have gotten
the double portion, this would have gotten the double portion, and from
here you see that the head coming out is considered birth. So
Michael is correct like, that requires, I mean, I see how you
get it sort of, I was, you know, I mean, I'm saying
I do see how you get it, but saying like, okay, that
requires real focus to see how you can get that out there,
but but is it so obvious? First of all, it's talking about
people not animals. Number two, it's so obvious that we would like
our משנה mishna. to repeat that within this context to explain the
implications. But the גמרא Gemara does assume that if you can infer
the same law, there would have been no reason to teach it
here, and the only question the גמרא Gemara is going to ask
is maybe it wouldn't be the same between animals and humans.
You have entire משניות mishnayot that are...
I get it. I get it. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. וכי תימא אשמעינן באדם וקא משמע לן בבהמה vechi teima
ashmian be'adam vekama shmalan biveheima
yes, that teaches me by humans that the head coming out is
considered born, but it doesn't teach me that that's true about animals.
So the גמרא Gemara says, דאדם מבהמה לא יליף de'adam mibeheima lo
yalif you can't infer humans from animals. Why not? דאין פרוזדור לבהמה
de'ein prozdor libeheima
because animals don't have a פרוזדור. prozdor. Now, what does this
mean? A פרוזדור prozdor literally means an antechamber. Now, here it means
the vag—well, it presumably means the vaginal canal except that רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot say it means something else. Now,
is it true that animals don't have a vaginal canal? I anybody
know? Charlie? I'm going to say since, I
mean, is the fetus carried, is the yeah, have uteruses
and vaginas. Uh-huh.
So the fetus is not carried right at the mouth of the
opening of the no. So okay, so that's interesting.
Well, right, for marsupials, marsupials and monotremes are different, but placental mammals
are all pretty much the same.
Okay, so there are places, this is very important because in הלכות
נדה Hilchot Niddah the anatomy in the גמרא Gemara in גמרא נדה
Gemara Niddah there's a discussion of פרוזדור prozdor and there's a question
what the פרוזדור prozdor means. And it's easiest to assume that the
פרוזדור prozdor means the vaginal canal and therefore, because it also makes
sense, you know, the antechamber, whatever, and here it's assuming, and then
the גמרא Gemara statement here would be that by animals that don't
have this vaginal canal, I might have thought that, you know, if
it doesn't have to go through the vaginal canal to come out,
so maybe maybe it's more ready to consider the animals if it's
born when it starts coming out at an earlier stage, if it
comes like straight from the womb outside, you know, there's no process
as much. That seems to be what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
However, as Charlie's informed us that that animals do have a vaginal
canal and also רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot while acknowledging that פרוזדור
prozdor usually means that, don't understand why that should make a difference
here. And what they say it means here is it means actually
the outside of the animal, which is another way of sort of
thinking about the antechamber, and it says, you know, for a female
animal, you know,
the the vagina, whatever, is directly exposed to the outside, there's it's
not hidden between the legs, and therefore, when the as soon as
the animal's head comes out, you see the animal. And therefore, you're
because we experience that birth, we see it immediately, the head, we're
more ready to consider it born as soon as the head comes
out. Whereas for a female human, because, you know, the the woman's
thighs are together and protect that space, so when the fetus comes
out, it's less visible immediately. And therefore, maybe I would not consider
it born until more of it came out. Now, this is a
little bizarre. to determine whether something is considered born based on how
visible it is to the outside observer as opposed to where it
actually is in the process, but that's how רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot both explain why this could make a difference. Okay, because
they acknowledge that that's not what פרוזדור prosdor usually means, but it's
the only way to explain and that actually solves the problem about
the anatomy because it's not making a claim about a different type
of an anatomy. So let's take a look now at that. Okay.
So therefore I don't understand what you just said. Okay. I mean,
if we use some more traditional words like crowning, right, when the
beginning...
But I was only hesitating to that because does crowning mean the
whole head or does crowning just mean... so I didn't want to
use the word crowning because, because it is true that you don't
need the whole head, you only need the majority of the head,
but I think somebody will say crowning even before the majority of
the head, right, like just the forehead, right? Okay, right. Okay, so
that's why I was avoiding that term. But go on. Okay, but
go on.
I don't really understand why you think that it
should matter between an animal and a woman
and why you've objected that by positing that it's more visible if
it's a four-legged
mammal, right?
Right. Yeah, it's very hard to
understand. You know, what they're basically saying is that at some, like,
experiential way to
us, do we experience it as the thing is born yet? If
it's, you know, if you have to pull it from between the
woman's legs, you don't fully experience it as born until more of
it comes out, perhaps. This was just a הוה אמינא, hava amina,
meaning why it was important to say the same law by animals
and humans. I shouldn't think that. I shouldn't think that because it
has to be pulled from between the
legs, you're not as ready to call it as born yet. But
I agree it's bizarre. You would normally say that it goes by
the stage of birth, not by what we're seeing visibly. So this
was just a הוה אמינא, hava amina, like why it would be
important to tell it in both places. Okay, so let's take a
look. Okay, דאדמי מבהמה לא ילף, de-adami mi-behema lo yalaf, if you
can't learn a person from an animal, דאין פרוזדור לבהמה, de-ein prosdor
le-behema, because since there's no ante-chamber, whatever that means for an animal,
I would have said there the head is enough. But by humans,
maybe you need more of it. ובהמה מאדם לא ילף, u-vehema me-adam
lo yalaf, if you can't learn animals from humans, why not just
say it by humans? By humans it's born by the head, not
by animal, and then I'll figure out animal. דחשיב פרצוף פנים דידי,
de-chashiv partzuf panim didei,
that's a nice explanation, because by humans we care about the faces
of humans. We don't really care so much about the faces of
animals. It doesn't say we care, it says it's significant. So the
idea that the head represents the body, the whole person, is more
something we think about in terms of humans, where the idea of
the face as representing the person, whereas we might not say the
same by animals, faces don't matter to us for animals. So maybe
there you need the majority of the animal, it's not symbolically representing
the entire person, the entire animal. That's, I think, a nice way
about thinking about that. Anyway, therefore you couldn't have said it by
both. So therefore, הנמי תנינא, hanami tanina,
so okay, but I have another place where we've already said even
by animals that the head is enough. Where do you get it?
The following משנה. mishna שליה שיצתה מקצתה, shilya she-yatzta miktzasa,
if a placenta comes out. Now the גמרא Gemara deals with, or
the משנה mishna deals with placentas that come out without any fetuses
with them. So it says if there's a placenta there has to
have been a fetus, and we have to assume that the fetus,
you know, that it was an aborted, disintegrated. I mean, that happens
in miscarriages, right? You'll get a lot of stuff coming out, you
won't see any fetus. So if a placenta comes out, we'll assume
that there's some type of
miscarried, dissolved fetus there, and therefore the presence of a placenta proves
fetus, and therefore the woman is considered to have given birth for
purposes of טומאה וטהרה, tum'ah ve-taharah, right? So therefore now, she is
considered טמאת לידה. temeiat leida. But for animals as well it matters,
because now let's say somebody wanted to eat the placenta. The משנה
mishna actually speaks about נפש היפה תאכלנה, nefesh ha-yafah tochlenna, which is
an euphemism, which is people that don't, are not finicky, and they're
interested in that. What, the same question, when is the placenta considered
to be born
and that therefore the שחיטה shechita. of the mother doesn't work for
it, and when is it not born and it's within the animal
and the שחיטה shechitah of the mother does work to allow you
to eat the placenta? So let's take a look. שליה שיצתה מקצתה,
shilya she-yatzta miktzasa, part of the placenta came out, אסורה באכילה, asura
ba-achila, you cannot eat any of the placenta, כסימן ולד באשה כך
סימן ולד בבהמה, kesiman vlad be-isha kach siman vlad be-vehema, because we
assume what? That if there's a placenta, there's a dissolved fetus with
it. And therefore if it's a dissolved fetus with it, maybe the
head of the fetus, what was the head of the fetus came
out, and therefore we have to assume that the whole placenta, fetus,
or whatever, is born, and therefore you can't eat it when you
now שוחט shocht the mother. Okay. So therefore, and it ends by
saying כסימן ולד באשה כך סימן ולד בבהמה. kesiman vlad be-isha kach
siman vlad be-vehema. So what is considered to be a sign of
childbirth by a mother is a sign of birth by an animal,
the head coming out, and here the placenta representing the head coming
out. So, yes.
How can you...
You go from placenta to head. Right. So this is quite bizarre.
There's two problems I should say with this. One is as Dov,
I think, is implicitly saying, is that... placenta that might prove that
some part of the fetus is considered born because by when a
little bit of the placenta we are concerned that it's the fetus
is there and it's born, but how do you know just the
head? So you know תוספות Tosfos tries...
what? Even if it used to be the head.
Right, and how do we know that that right now? Right. So
that's assumed to be... that's assumed to be because otherwise it wouldn't
even be a concept of being born here, right? Because then the
placenta would just be like some organ, some other thing inside of
the בהמה, behema, but the other thing
is how do you know that it's because it represents the head?
You know, who knows what it's supposed to represent? So it just
says well because it's part of the placenta, so part of the
placenta could only represent a part of the body and therefore the
only part that would make sense would be the head. But it's
a big jump, it's a little bit of a jump. We'll just
say one other problem is I was waiting for somebody to ask,
none of these discussions about when is it considered born discuss the
case of pulling the head back. So you could have said even
if we could have inferred from there that the head is considered
born, maybe our משנה mishna is coming to tell you that even
after it's pulled the head back it's already considered born. Okay so
תוספות Tosfos says well maybe yeah but you wouldn't have had to
say a whole big משנה mishna just to tell us that one
point. So, so the גמרא Gemara is trying to prove that the
משנה mishna is redundant but actually it does not seem so redundant
for those two reasons. Yes.
Is there a birth canal in bovine
animals?
Okay.
There yeah, all
mammals.
Okay.
There
you go.
Wikipedia. Okay. All right, all right, so let's keep on going. All
right, this is a tough גמרא, Gemara, let's work together to get
through it. Okay. So anyway so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So אי אמרת בשלמא imarta bishlama so now we have somewhat demonstrated
that, that we already know the idea that the head coming out
is considered like the fetus is born and now we say that
therefore that can't be the point of the משנה mishna to tell
us just that law. The point of the משנה mishna also has
to tell us something about the first half about just sticking out
the limb. So let's take a look. אי אמרת בשלמא החזירה דרישא
דוקא, imarta bishlama hachizira deraysha davka, תנא
דוקא, tana davka, if the point about pulling the limb back was
to tell a point that the limb while it's out is forbidden
but once it's back it becomes permissible and the point of the
first part of the משנה mishna? was to tell you the limb
does become permissible when it's pulled back, so תנא סיפא אטו רישא,
tana seifa atu reisha, it talks about the end about the head
coming out because we had it because the emphasis was the beginning
that the limb becomes permissible. אלא אי אמרת לא דרישא דוקא ella
imarta lo deraysha davka that the first part wasn't merely emphasizing pulling
the limb back because the limb remains forbidden, so whether the limb
is or is not pulled back doesn't matter, ולא דסיפא דוקא ve-lo
deseifa davka and the end isn't really telling you anything, any חידוש
chiddush about the head coming out because that we already know from
other places that the head coming out is considered being born and
we don't have to teach it, so למה לי למיתנייה כלל, lama
li le-misna’ei klal, so what's the whole point of the משנה? mishna
So again what it's trying to say is rather than reading the
משנה mishna which we assumed is פשט, pshat, which is that the
חידוש chiddush? of the משנה mishna is that it's considered born when
the head comes out and as תוספות Tosfos already points out, even
if you know the idea from other places that the head is
considered born, the משנה mishna. telling you that even pulling it back
it's still considered born, but the גמרא Gemara is saying no, no,
no, that, that's really not the point of the משנה. mishna The
point of the משנה mishna we know that already, point of the
משנה mishna has to be the beginning and if the point is
the beginning, what's the חידוש? chiddush The חידוש chiddush must be that
when it pulls the limb back the limb becomes permissible. So how
can you say that when it pulls the limb back the limb
remains forbidden? That's the question. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara
answer is. גמרא Gemara says לא לעולם אבר, lo le'olam eivar, really
the חידוש chiddush here is not that the limb becomes permissible and
I'll accept the חידוש chiddush is not the סיפא, seifa, so what's
the חידוש chiddush? then? כדאמר רב נחמן בר יצחק ke-di-amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak לא נצרכה אלא למקום חתך, lo nitzercha ela lemakom chata,
like what רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak is going
to say on עמוד ב, amud beis, the only point of this
that the only point of this משנה mishna, was to tell you
about the place of cutting. הכא נמי לא נצרכה אלא למקום חתך,
hacha nami lo nitzercha ela lemakom chata, here too that's the point
of this משנה, Mishnah it's only to tell you about the place
of cutting. What does that mean? What it means is that, you
know, the גמרא Gemara loves this and I also love this about
the things which are like, you know, are out of one category
but not yet in the other. In order for, if we assume
that there's a problem of a limb going out and becoming forbidden
even when it comes back in because of the idea of בשר
בשדה טרפה, basar basadeh treifa, so the emphasis there is בשדה, left
its right zone. So if you imagine a limb sticking out, right,
here, here is this limb sticking out of the mother. Okay. This
is the part that's out, this is the part that's in. There's
a part right here on the line that is can neither be
called out or in. Okay? So from the perspective of the idea
of בשר בשדה טרפה, basar basadeh treifa, does it become טרפה treifa
because it was out of its zone? Well it's not out, it's
right on the line. We can only say the part that's beyond
that line itself. But how about if you were to שחט shecht
the mother right now? When you שחט shecht the mother, what makes
the fetus permissible? It's based on a verse that says בהמה, behema,
the דרשה drasha is בהמה בבהמה. behema bevehema. If an animal is
in an animal then the then that becomes permissible through
the
שחיטה. shechitah So, if the limb is out that and you שחט
shecht the mother, that line remains forbidden because it's not in. If
the limb gets pulled back, it's true the part that was out
remains forbidden, that was בשדה, that was out, but now the line
is now in the mother. So that מקום חיתוך makom chituch now
becomes permissible. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah. is now teaching me if
it pulls the limb back, the limb remains forbidden because that was
outside, but the part that was exactly on the line, now that
that's being pulled back into the mother, it wasn't outside, but it
wasn't in, and now it is inside, now that does become permissible.
Exactly. Well, you have to be precise, you have to be safe.
Okay. תא שמע, Ta shema, that's where we are. But now the
גמרא's Gemara going to go and try again to prove is this
really true that the limb remains forbidden. בהמה מקשה לילד, Behemah maksheh
lileid, so הוציא עובר ידו, hotzi ubar yado, so this is a
ברייתא braita that parallels our משנה. Mishnah So an animal is giving
childbirth, and the fetus sticks out its hand. והחזירה, vehichzirah, and pulls
it back. ואחר שחט אמו, veachar shachat imo, and then you שחט
shecht? the mother. מותר באכילה, mutar baachilah, you can eat it. Again,
what's it? The fetus or even the limb? That will be discussed.
שחט אמו ואחר כך החזירה, shachat imo veachar kach heichzirah, you שחט
shecht the mother when the limb was outside and then it pulled
the limb back in or it doesn't really matter. אסור באכילה, asur
baachilah, it is forbidden. Now that seems to be quite clear that
that's our point. Right? It says if it pulled the limb back
and you שחט it, it's permitted. If it didn't pull the limb
back and you שחט it, it's forbidden. The it seems here to
be clearly be the limb because the fetus in either case is
permissible and it seems to be exactly this. That if the limb
is back in, it's okay. If it's not back in, it's no
good. Okay, let's just finish the ברייתא. braita. הוציא את ידו וחתכה
ואחר שחט אמו, hotzia et yado vechatcho veachar shachat imo,
it stuck out its limb and you chopped its limb off. Now
you could also imagine this because this goes back to why we're
saying it's מקשה לילד. maksheh lileid. It's having difficulty in childbirth. Because
this you could imagine the גמרא Gemara has these cases, משנה Mishna,
has these cases by women as well. That the woman's life is
in danger and you have to actually abort the fetus, right, in
order to save the life of the mother. So here you have
that case by the cow. The fetus is sticking out its limb,
you know, also that's bizarre, right? Sticking out its limb, not its
head. So you're cutting the limb off in order to get the
fetus out to save the mother. Okay, so you cut off the
limb while it's stuck out and then you שחט the mother. Then
you just said looks like this mother's gonna die, let's שחט it
now before it dies. Right? You could imagine that as well. So
you שחט the mother. ואחר שחט אמו, veachar shachat imo, שבחוץ טמא.
shebechutz tamei. So what you cut off is אבר מן החי. eiver
min hachai. Okay, actually it's a question whether it's אבר מן החי,
eiver min hachai, but it's a limb that never had a kosher
שחיטה shechitah done to it, right? It was something that, this was
a limb that never had a kosher שחיטה shechitah done to it.
So what is the status of this limb that you cut off?
So שבחוץ טמא shebechutz tamei is, it causes טומאה tumah because we
actually consider it to be אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, which
is quite interesting, right? When you cut up the fetus in the
mother, it's not אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, but when you
cut up the limb that sticks out, now it's already a limb
in the world, אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, and אבר מן
החי eiver min hachai causes טומאה, tumah, yes, ואסור, veasur, and it's
forbidden. ושבפנים, veshebifnim, the fetus inside, טהור ומותר, tahor umutar, is טהור
tahor and permissible. שחט אמו ואחר חתכה. shachat imo veachar chatcho.
Now it had the limb sticking out and you שחט the mother.
So what's the status now of the limb that is sticking out
if you שחט the mother while the limb was sticking out? It's
not אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, right, because you didn't cut
it when the animal was alive, but it was a part, but
it didn't have a שחיטה shechitah done to it. The שחיטה shechitah?
applied to the mother and the fetus, not to this extended limb.
So what is the status? So it's meat that doesn't have שחיטה
shechitah, done to it. What do we normally call meat that doesn't
have the benefit of שחיטה? shechitah טריפה tereifah or נבילה. neveilah.
So that's going to be the question. So let's take a look.
So it says הבשר, habasar, the remaining meat, the meat of the
mother and the fetus is מגע נבילה, maga neveilah, דברי רבי מאיר.
divrei Rabbi Meir. Meaning the limb is considered נבילה, neveilah, meat without
the benefit of שחיטה, shechitah and the other part of the mother
that touched this limb is meat that has touched a נבילה. neveilah.
That's just for טומאה tumah purposes.
וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, but the sages say מגע טריפה שחוטה. maga
tereifah shechutah. No, it is considered like if it's considered a טריפה,
tereifah, not a נבילה. neveilah. Now טריפה tereifah really doesn't have טומאה,
tumah, but there is some rabbinic טומאה tumah for it. So anyway,
they say the meat is like a טריפה, tereifah, which is interesting
because they basically say it's not like there was no שחיטה shechitah.
at all. There was a שחיטה shechitah on the mother. It just
didn't work. So that actually is more like טריפה, tereifah, right? נבילה
neveilah is it died without שחיטה. shechitah טריפה tereifah is that there
was שחיטה shechitah but the שחיטה shechitah didn't work. So that's an
interesting question. What do we think about this limb that was stuck
out when the mother was שחט? Is it like there was no
שחיטה shechita on the limb, then it's נבילה? neveilah? Do we say
there was שחיטה shechita that took place but it didn't work for
the limb, then it's like a טריפה? tereifah? Okay, so that's an
interesting question, but we're going to bracket that and go to our
point. Our point says whether it pulls the limb out in or
out determines whether it's permissible or forbidden. So it sounds like the
limb becomes permissible when it comes back in. Let's take a look.
תני מיהא, tani miheia, we teach nonetheless, רישא, reisha, in the beginning,
הוציא עובר ידו והחזירה, hotzi ubar yado vehichzirah, it stuck out its
limb and pulled it back, ואחר שחט אמו, veachar shachat imo, and
then it שחט the mother, מותר באכילה, mutar baachilah, it is permissible.
מאי לאו האבר, mai lav haeiver, presumably that means the limb? it
becomes permissible. לא העובר lo ha-ubar no the fetus. Papa says no,
you can't say that. אי העובר ei ha-ubar if we're talking here
about the fetus, אימא סיפא eima seifa let's look at the next
case in this ברייתא. braita. שחט את אמו ואחר כך החזירה shachat
et imo ve-achar kach hichzirah if you slaughtered the mother and then
it pulled its limb back in, אסור באכילה asur beachila it is
forbidden. What's it? ואי העובר אמאי אסור ve-ei ha-ubar amai asur if
we're talking about the fetus, why is it forbidden? The fetus never
becomes forbidden just because of the limb. So since this ברייתא braita
very clearly says that if the limb is out, it's forbidden, if
the limb is in, it's permissible, and the it cannot refer to
the fetus, clearly the it refers to the limb. And you see
when the limb comes back in, it's permissible.
This contradicts Rav earlier that says that the limb remains forbidden. So
the Gemara says אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak once again, this is the answer we pull out of our
pocket when we have this question on Rav, לא נצרכה אלא למקום
חתך lo nitzrecha ela lemekom chataach we need it for the actual
that line, the line of cutting. הכא נמי לא נצרכה אלא למקום
חתך hacha nami lo nitzrecha ela lemekom chataach even in the line
of cutting. It is the מקום חתך. mekom chataach. The fetus is
of course always permissible, it wasn't born yet. The limb is always
forbidden because the limb was בשר בשדה טריפה, basar basadeh tereifah, but
what matters whether it pulled it in or not is whether that
line which was neither in nor out becomes permissible or not. Pretty
big stretch, okay? If it wasn't mentioned at all and all of
a sudden it's referred to by an it, okay, yes. Clearly the
evidence of all of this seems to be that the limb once,
that against Rav that when the limb is pulled back it's fine.
Okay, let's take a look. איני eini is that really true? והא
כי אתא אבימי מבי חוזאי veha ki ata Avimi mibei Chuzaei and
now we're going to see the first the other place where he
said this idea of the
מקום חתך. mekom chataach. When Abimi came from the house of Chuzaei,
אתא ואייתי מתניתא בידיה ata ve-aytei matnita bidei
he came and he brought the following ברייתא, braita, meaning he was
in the בית מדרש beis medrash of this place of Bei Chuzaei
and he was taught the following ברייתא braita and he came and
he reported it to us. And here it is, it's a nice
little דרשה drasha on the פסוק. pasuk How do we know inside
that the fetus inside a mother is permissible? Because we learn it
from a פסוק pasuk that
says כל בהמה מפרסת פרסה ושסעת שסע שתי פרסות מעלת גרה בבהמה
אותה תאכלו kol behemah mafreset parsah veshashat shesa shetei parasot maalat gerah
babehemah otah tocheilu any animal that has split hooves whatever amongst the
animals אותה תאכלו. otah tocheilu. And we make a דרשה drasha we
say בבהמה בבהמה babehemah babehemah an animal within an animal you can
eat. Okay, we sort of take out the middle words. So if
an animal is a fetus is within the mother you can eat
it. And now the question is we're going to do a דרשה
drasha on that דרשה. drasha. Because in that פסוק pasuk it says
כל בהמה אשר היא מפרסת פרסה kol behemah asher hi mafreset parsah
hoof ושסעת שסע שתי פרסות veshashat shesa shetei parasot hooves. So we're
going to say within these fetuses within the mother that you can
eat, there are cases of a hoof and there are cases of
hooves. Let's take a look at what that means. Okay, so here's
the ברייתא braita that he teaches.
פרסה parsah a hoof, החזיר אכול hechezir echol if it pulls back
its hoof you can eat it.
פרסות parasot hooves, החזיר אכול hechezir echol if it pulls them back
you can eat it. So we need the reason it says in
the middle hoof and hooves is to tell you that if it
sticks out one arm or two arms as long as it pulls
it back you can eat it.
You say hoof, you don't?
All right, why have to say both, we'll worry about it later.
But anyway, it again seems to be emphasizing that when it pulls
the limb back you can eat the limb. If פרסה parsah if
it's החזיר אכול. hechezir echol. So the ברייתא braita says so, so
the Gemara says like this:
מאי לאו mai lav does this not mean החזיר פרסה אכול פרסה
hechezir parsah echol parsah if it pulls back the limb you can
eat the limb, if it pulls back the hoof eat the hoof?
So the Gemara says לא lo no, החזיר פרסה אכול עובר hechezir
parsah echol ubar if it pulls back the hoof you can eat
the fetus. Gemara says wait, that doesn't make sense, you don't need
it to do that. אי עובר ei ubar if it's the fetus
מאי איריא החזיר mai irya hechezir who cares if you pulled back
the hoof? אפילו לא החזיר נמי afilu lo hechezir nami even without
doing it. And here is where the statement was originally said אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak לא נצרכה אלא
למקום חתך lo nitzrecha ela lemekom chataach once again, the place of
the cutting. So if it pulled back the hoof, not you can
eat the hoof, what can you eat? That line which was neither
in nor out. Okay, now the Gemara says come on, to tell
me that you don't have to say both פרסה parsah and פרסות
parasot twice. So the Gemara says והא תרי קראי כתיב לה veha
trei krei kasiv lah it says two פסוקים pesukim hoof and hooves.
So even if I grant you that one פסוק pasuk could tell
you about this line, but by the time you get to the
second thing about hooves, at least it should be telling you that
that leg itself is permissible. So the Gemara says מאי לאו חד
לאבר וחד למקום חתך mai lav chad le-eiver vechad lemekom chataach is
it not that one one might be telling you the line is
okay, but by the time if you have two things, hoof and
hooves, the other one presumably is telling you that actually the limb
is okay. So the Gemara says לא not necessarily, חד למקום חתך
chad lemekom chataach one like we said is just permitting this line
that was neither in nor out. The hoof, the limb remains forbidden.
וחד לקולט בדמי פרה vechad lekolat bidmei parah what is the other
one? Let's say you have an animal that is born from a
cow that its hooves look like camel's hooves. Its hooves are not
cleft hooves. Okay, so there's a position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that we're going to quote in a minute. Now normally you would
assume anything born from a kosher animal is kosher. Okay, but there
is a position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that if
you have an animal that's born from a cow with uncloven hooves,
unsplit hooves or whatever, it is not kosher. So for according to
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we are saying that only once it's born
and is independent, but if as long as it's in the mother's
womb, it's a part of the mother, it's okay. And that's what
we learn from the word פרסה parsa because פרסה parsa as opposed
to פרסות parsot means it has a hoof, not hooves, meaning it's
not split hooves. So if you have a פרסה parsa in an
animal, as long as it's still in the mother and not yet
born, then it's okay. So one of the verses teaches us this
מקום חתך, makom hatach, the other teaches us this uncloven, unsplit-hoofed cow
in the mother's womb, and neither of them tell us the limb
itself becomes permitted.
But then it's not been born yet
either, you're not after that point. Right, but okay,
but we're saying it's okay, that's exactly the point. So you face
אי הכי נמי. ei hachi nami. So the Gemara says, oh, you're
just saying so what's the חידוש? Right, but the other way it
had the potential for doing it. Okay. ואליבא דרבי שמעון, v'aliba deRebbi
Shimon, according to רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, דאמר רבי שמעון, d'amar Rebbi
Shimon, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says קלוט בן פרה, kalut ben parah,
a non-split hoofed child of a cow, אסור is forbidden. הני מילי
היכא דנפק לאויר עולם, hani mili heicha denefak l'avir olam, that's only
when it comes out to the air of the world, it's born.
אבל במעי אמו, aval b'mei imo, if it was in the mother's
womb, שרי shari it's permissible and we learn that from פרסה בבהמה,
parsa babeheimah, even if it only has a hoof and not hooves
in the mother. So we have all of this evidence that the
simple sense of all the משנה, all the ברייתא, Braita, whatever, everything
seems to say that while the limb is outside it's a problem
because then the שחיטה shechita doesn't apply to the limb, but as
soon as the limb comes inside it's okay. And the way we
got out of all of that was we introduced this idea of
מקום חתך, makom hatach, neither in, neither out. That becomes okay when
pulled back. But רב Rav is asserting once it's out, it remains
forbidden. It's this idea of בשר בשדה. basar basadeh. Now we are
finally going to have an expression of the opinion that has been
in the background the whole time that disagrees with רב. Rav. Let's
take a look.
Okay. עולא
אמר רבי יוחנן, Ulla amar Rebbi Yochanan, and עולא Ulla says in
the name of רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, ואבר עצמו, v'eiver atzmo, where
are you, עולא אמר רבי יוחנן ואבר עצמו מותר. Ulla amar Rebbi
Yochanan v'eiver atzmo mutar. You're wrong. When you pull the limb back,
the limb is permissible. The only problem with the limb is it
didn't get a שחיטה shechita if it was out when the שחיטה
was taking place. But if it was in when the שחיטה was
taking place, it's totally fine. אמר ליה רב יהודה לעולא, amar lei
Rav Yehuda l'Ulla, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said to עולא, Ulla,
והא רב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו, veha Rav uShmuel de-amri taryehu, but one
minute, we only before heard in the name of רב. Rav. Now
we're going to hear שמואל Shmuel agreed with him. But didn't רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, רב Rav and שמואל... Shmuel... so you notice by
the way he was saying this. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda who was
the one that said the original statement? רב יהודה Rav Yehuda אמר
רב. Rav Okay, so here עולא Ulla says in רבי יוחנן's Rebbi
Yochanan name the exact opposite position, the limb becomes permissible. רב Rav
יהודה who was the tradition of רב's Rav statement who says the
limb is forbidden is now challenging עולא. Ulla. And here what he's
saying. והא רב
ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו, veha Rav uShmuel de-amri taryehu, both רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel say אבר עצמו אסור, eiver atzmo assur, the limb remains
forbidden.
אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, מאן יהיב לן
מעפר דרב ושמואל ומלינא עינא. man yahiv lan mei'afar deRav uShmuel umalina
einan. So first he praises רב Rav, and שמואל. Shmuel. He says,
who could give us from the dust of where רב and שמואל
Shmuel trample and I would so treasure their dust I would put
it in my eyes. So it's like I, of course, I worship
the dust that they walk on. That being said, however, right, אלא,
ela, no,
no, that's not what they're saying Bobby. He's really, it's a real
statement of real veneration. But it's still saying that you're entitled to
have a different opinion. So, okay, I hear that they say it,
I worship the ground they walk on. אלא הכא אמר רבי יוחנן.
ela hacha amar Rebbi Yochanan. I'm telling you, here's what רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan says. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says הכל היו בכלל בשר
בשדה טרפה. hakol hayu bichlal basar basadeh tereifah. So again, we're learning
this on this idea of בשר בשדה טרפה. basar basadeh tereifah. רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says it's true. The idea of בשר בשדה טרפה
basar basadeh tereifah communicates an idea of things out of their zone
become forbidden. And that would have included everything. קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim
that would have left the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash קדשים קלים kodshim
kalim, that would have left ירושלים. Yerushalayim A fetus's limb that would
have gone out of the mother's womb. All of those things in
theory would have been included. However,
כשפירט לך הכתוב גבי חטאת, keshepierat lecha hakatuv gabei chatat, when the
Torah explicitly said by a sin offering שיצאת חוץ ממחיצתה וחזרה אסורה,
sheyatzta chutz mimchitzata vechazra asura, when it went outside it's forbidden. Where
did it say this? I'll talk about it in a minute. But
he's going to say the Torah explicitly said that by the sin
offering when it goes out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash חטאת
הוא דפירט רחמנא בה. chatat hu depirat Rachmana bah. That then we
now learn that this principle only applies to a חטאת. chatat By
the חטאת, chatas, by קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim, where the Torah says
explicitly, that's where when it goes out of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash. it's forbidden and remains forbidden. אבל כל מילי, aval kol mili,
everything else, even קרבנות, korbanot, even if a שלמים goes out of
ירושלים Yerushalayim, and certainly things that are not קרבנות korbanot like this
fetus, anything else this principle does not apply. כיון דהדר, keivan dehader,
once it goes back, שרי shari it becomes permissible. So he basically
said, I don't agree with this whole big דרשה drasha of בשר
בשדה טרפה. basar basadeh tereifah. It only applies to a sin offering.
Where do we get it by a sin offering? We get it
by משה Moshe who inquires after חז"ל Chazal learn a lot of
הלכה by משה Moshe who inquires after the שעיר החטאת, se'ir hachatat,
right, the goat sin offering that was burnt on the eighth day
of the מילואים Milu'im and it says, הן לא הובא את דמה
אל הקדש פנימה. hen lo huva et dama el hakodesh pnimah. Its
blood wasn't brought into the inner chamber. Now that's saying to us
if you bring the blood of a חטאת into the קדשי קדשים,
then you burn it. So משה Moshe says why'd you burn it?
You didn't do that. But חז"ל Chazal make a play on that
פסוק and they say first of all הן לא הובא את דמה.
hen lo huva et dama. First of all the blood wasn't brought
in. so that's not a reason to burn it. Number two, let's
say you say oh maybe the meat was taken outside of the
בית המקדש of the משכן Mishkan and therefore we're going to burn
it? No, פנימה, Pnima, it remained on the inside. So the פנימה
Pnima is not going on the no, פנימה's Pnima an assertion. So
since it remained on the inside, that's not a reason to burn
it either. Meaning that
if it were brought outside the משכן Mishkan it would have been
burned. So from there חז"ל Chazal understand that משה Moshe was saying
this idea that if it was brought outside it would be burned.
And רבי בונים Rebbe Bunim is saying, ah, that's the only time.
By a חטאת, something that has to stay in the בית המקדש.
But anything else, even קדשי קלים kodshei kalim in ירושלים Yerushalayim and
certainly a fetus in its mother's womb going out of its home
zone, you know, out of its boundaries, does not make it forbidden.
Okay so let's just end this line. One more thing to tie
this up. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
מיתיבי, Meisvei, I'll ask you on that. So בשר בשדה טרפה לא
תאכלו. basar basadeh treifa lo socheilu. We have a ברייתא. braisa. Meat
that is again this פסוק that is in the field. מה תלמוד
לומר, ma talmud lomar, what does that teach? לפי שמצינו במעשר שני
וביכורים, Lefi shematzinu bemaaser sheni uvikurim, because we found by non קרבנות,
korbanos, things like מעשר שני maaser sheni and ביכורים bikurim that have
to be eaten in ירושלים, שאף על פי שיצאו חוץ למחיצתן וחזרו
מותרים, sheaf al pi sheyatziu chutz mechitasan vechazru mutarin, that those if
you take them out of ירושלים and bring them back they're okay.
יכול אף זה כן, Yachol af zeh ken, perhaps even this. Now
what's the even this? Even this could mean
קדשים קלים, but we're assuming that the context here is the fetus
and its limb. So maybe here too the limb pulling back would
be okay. תלמוד לומר טרפה. Talmud lomar treifa. So it says no,
טרפה. So מאי תלמודא, mai talmuda, where do you get this? So
אמר רבה, Amar Rabba, כטרפה, ketreifa, just like the טרפה. מה טרפה
כיון שנטרפה שוב אין לה היתר, Ma treifa kivan shenitrefa shuv ein
lah heter, the same way once an animal became a טרפה it
doesn't become permissible, although we talked about that remember whether a hole
gets filled later and so on, but okay. אף בשר, Af basar,
even meat, כיון שיצא חוץ למחיצתו שוב אין לו היתר, kivan sheyatza
chutz mechitaso shuv ein lo heter, once it went out of its
boundaries no longer is permissible. So this is a ברייתא braisa which
says explicitly that this verse about בשר בשדה טרפה basar basadeh treifa
teaches you that when the limb goes out of its zone, it
remains forbidden although the context isn't so 100% clear. And the גמרא
Gemara says that this ברייתא braisa proves the whole debate.
תיובתא דעולא תיובתא. Tyufta deUlla tyufta. That is a contradiction to עולא
Ulla which is really not at all an absolute contradiction, not at
all what you thought we were ending up. Right for us, all
of the evidence seemed to indicate that pulling the limb back in
it became permissible. Even if this last ברייתא braisa means that it's
saying that the limb remains forbidden, at most we would say fine,
that's an opinion of one ברייתא. braisa. But all of the other
evidence seems strongly say that the limb is permitted. Interestingly though the
גמרא Gemara weighs in favor of this ברייתא, braisa, assumes everything else
was just talking about that מקום חתך makom chetach and weighs up
arguing in favor, you know, deciding in favor of רב, that once
the limb goes out it remains forbidden even if pulled back.